<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE visualization SYSTEM "../../visualization.dtd">
<visualization name="Phylogenetic Aequatus" embeddable="true">
    <description>Gene Structure and Homology</description>
    <data_sources>
        <data_source>
            <model_class>HistoryDatasetAssociation</model_class>
            <test test_attr="ext">gafa.sqlite</test>
        </data_source>
    </data_sources>
    <params>
        <param required="true">dataset_id</param>
    </params>
    <entry_point entry_point_type="script" src="index.js" />
    <tests>
        <test>
            <param name="dataset_id" value="http://cdn.jsdelivr.net/gh/galaxyproject/galaxy-test-data/1.gafa.sqlite" ftype="gafa.sqlite" />
        </test>
    </tests>
    <help format="markdown"><![CDATA[
# What is Phylogenetic Aequatus?

Aequatus is an interactive visualization tool for exploring gene structure and homology relationships across multiple species. It provides an intuitive and informative way to view and compare intron/exon structures, synteny, and evolutionary events such as gene duplications and losses.

After selecting a compatible dataset (e.g., Ensembl-compliant gene trees or comparative genomics data), Aequatus will display an interactive graphical representation of the data directly in your browser.

## Key Features

- **Gene Structure Visualization**: View exon/intron structures across homologous genes, aligned against a reference gene.
- **Homology Exploration**: Distinguish orthologs and paralogs with clear visual cues.
- **Interactive Interface**: Zoom, pan, and inspect individual gene models for detailed annotations.
- **Synteny View**: Explore conserved gene order and structure between species.
- **Custom Annotations**: Display additional metadata and tooltips for enhanced understanding.

This tool is particularly useful for comparative genomics and evolutionary biology studies, allowing researchers to investigate how genes have diverged or remained conserved across species.

To learn more about the Aequatus platform, visit the original publication:
[Aequatus: An open-source homology browser](https://academic.oup.com/gigascience/article/7/11/giy128/5160135)
    ]]></help>
</visualization>
