<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tool id="getLPed" name="Import ped/map new">
	<description>
		from your computer  
	</description>
       <action module="galaxy.tools.actions.lpedupload" class="UploadLpedToolAction" />
 	<inputs>
 	  <param name="title" type="text" size="80" value="My lped upload" />
          <param name="ped_file_data" type="file" label="Ped (alternative to URL) Local file"
            help="Navigate to a Linkage format pedigree file on your local PC" />
          <param name="ped_url_paste" type="text" label="(alternative to local file) URL/Text" help="URL for ped data to download" />
          <param name="map_file_data" type="file" label="Matching map (alternative to URL) Local file"
            help="Navigate to a Linkage format map corresponding to the above ped file on your local PC" />
          <param name="map_url_paste" type="text" label="(alternative to local file) URL/Text" 
            help="URL for corresponding map data to download" />
           <param label="Genome" name="dbkey" type="genomebuild" dynamic_options="get_available_builds('hg18')" />
	</inputs>

	<outputs>  
          <data format="rgenetics" name="outfile" />
	</outputs>
<help>


**Syntax**

- **Note - Exactly one Ped and the corresponding Map are needed** Either can be a file from your local machine or a web address
- **Ped file data** is the input pedigree format genotype file chosen from your local files
- **Map file data** is the associated annotation (map) file for the markers in the Ped file
- **Ped URL** is the web address for the pedigree format genotype file 
- **Map URL** is the associated annotation (map) web address for the markers in the Ped file 


Ped - space delimited. First 6 cols are famId,individualId, fatherId, motherId, gender, affection status.
Genotypes as a1 a2 follow - letters ACGTN or 12340 typically

Map (marker annotation) tab delimited,
four columns - Chromosome, rs, genetic offset, physical offset"

-----

**Summary**

This tool imports genotype data from a high throughput snp platform into the Rgenetics tools
for Galaxy. Data in linkage (ped and map files) format are currently importable. The data will 
be converted to a slew of other formats and imported into the current history.

A bunch of conversions are done and the results are visible in the data set selection
drop down list for each relevant tool. For example, all the Plink based tools will 
show your new data from now on and same for Marchini's tools and eigenstrat.

Always check the log file (click the "view" (eye) icon) after this tool runs as 
you may need to adjust the missing value if you see a message like:
<pre>
ERROR: Locus rs1063302 has >2 alleles:
       individual 1334 10 has genotype [ N N ]
       but we've already seen [ G ] and [ A ]
</pre>

Originally designed and written for family based data from the CAMP Illumina run of 2007 by 
ross lazarus (ross.lazarus@gmail.com)

Once a file has been imported, it will be available for selection as the input data for tools in the Rgenetics menu that 
operate on the various output files

</help>
</tool>
