<tool id="rgGvarICC1" name="GeneVar ICC:">
    <code file="listFiles.py"/> 
    <code file="rgClean_code.py"/> 
  
    <description>Test GeneVar expression for signal/noise ratio</description>
  
    <command interpreter="python">
        rgGvarICC.py $name $genelist $race out_file1
    </command>
    
    <inputs>    
       <param name="name" type="text" label="Output workspace filename" value="rgGvar_test"/>
       <param name="genelist" type="text" size="50" label="Comma separated HUGO symbols (eg TLR4,IL10)" value="" /> 
       <param type="select" name="race" label="HapMap Panel" help="Hapmap panel to select">
                        <option value="CEU" selected="yes">CEPH trios</option>
                        <option value="YRI">Yoruba trios</option>
                        <option value="JPT">Japanese</option>
                        <option value="CHB">Chinese</option>
       </param>
   </inputs>

   <outputs>  
       <data format="txt" name="out_file1" />
   </outputs>
<help>


**Syntax**

- **Output name** is the name to use for the results output file in your current workspace
- **Comma separated genelist** is a list of genes you want to test
- **Hapmap panel** is the race to select expression data from

-----

**Summary**

This tool tests all the probes in the Illumina u6 Sanger_ GeneVar data to see if
there is more variability within the quantile normalized log2 transformed values from 4 
replicates per subject (2 replicated arrays from each of 2 separate IVT reactions per sample), than 
between all the subjects, using the intra-class correlation (ICC) estimated from an ANOVA. 

If this test rejects the null hypothesis, the probe may well contain real signal and may be worth
further analysis. If not, there's more technical replicate
variability than there is variation between subjects, so it seems that there is not likely to 
be much useful signal - if the variability between technical replicates
within a single cell line is greater than the variability between subjects, that cannot be good! 
It turns out that the method rejects about half of all the Illumina U6 probes used in the Sanger_ data
and there is reasonable consistency between the 4 population panels.


Originally designed and written for the Rgenetics_ project in June 2007 by 
ross lazarus (ross.lazarus@gmail.com) and Weiliang Qiu. Sanger GeneVar data is from the Sanger_ website.

  .. _Rgenetics: http://rgenetics.org
  .. _Sanger: http://www.sanger.ac.uk/humgen/genevar

</help>
</tool>
