<tool id="rgPbat1" name="Pbat for family genotypes">
    <code file="listFiles.py"/> 
    <code file="rgPbat_code.py"/> 
  
    <description>Pbat Statistical models and tests</description>
  
    <command interpreter="python2.4">
        plinkPbat.py $pedf $phef $jobname $phecols $depvar $outformat $out_file1 $logf $map
    </command>
    
    <inputs>   
    <page> 
       <param name="pedf"  type="select" label="Rgenetics Genotype file in linkage ped format" format="lped" size="80"/> 
       <param name="phef"  type="select" label="Rgenetics Phenotype file" format="pphe" size="80"/> 
       <param name='jobname' label='Job Name' type='text' value='GLM' />
       <param name="outformat" type="select" label="Format of file to output" dynamic_options="get_out_formats()" />
    </page>
    <page>
      <param name="phecols"  type="select" label="Covariates" dynamic_options="get_phecols(phef)" /> 
    </page>
    </inputs>

   <outputs>  
       <data format="txt" name="out_file1" />
       <data format="txt" name="logf" parent="out_file1" />
   </outputs>
<help>


**Syntax**

- **Genotype file** is the input family data chosen from available library compressed files
- **Phenotype file** is the input phenotype file with iid and famid followed by phenotypes 
- **Dependant variable** is the term on the left of the model
- **Covariates** are covariate terms on the right of the model  
- **Map file** is the linkage format .map file corresponding to the genotypes in the Genotype file 
- **Format** determines how your data will be returned to your Galaxy workspace


**Summary**

This tool will run pbat

If you don't see the genotype or phenotype data set you want here, it can be imported using 
one of the methods available from the Galaxy Get Data tool page.

Output format can be UCSC .bed if you want to see your 
results as a fully fledged UCSC track. A map file containing the chromosome and offset for each marker is required for
writing this kind of output.
Alternatively you can use .gg for the UCSC Genome Graphs tool which has all of the advantages
of the the .bed track, plus a neat, visual front end that displays a lot of useful clues. 
Either of these are a very useful way of quickly getting a look
at your data in full genomic context. 

Finally, if you can't live without 
spreadsheet data, choose the .xls tab delimited format. It's not a stupid binary excel file. Just a plain old tab delimited 
one with a header. Fortunately excel is dumb enough to open these without much protest.



-----


**Attribution**

Originally designed and written for the Rgenetics
series of Galaxy tools by ross lazarus (ross.lazarus@gmail.com), who didn't write either Galaxy or Plink
but wishes he had.

</help>
</tool>
