<tool id="compute_p-values_max_variances_feature_occurrences_in_one_dataset_using_discrete_wavelet_transfom" name="Compute P-values and Max Variances for Feature Occurrences" version="1.0.0">
  <description>in one dataset using Discrete Wavelet Transfoms</description>
  
  <command interpreter="perl">
  	execute_dwt_var_perClass.pl $inputFile $outputFile1 $outputFile2 $outputFile3
  </command>
  
  <inputs>
  	<param format="tabular" name="inputFile" type="data" label="Select the input file"/>	
  </inputs>
  
  <outputs>
    <data format="tabular" name="outputFile1"/> 
    <data format="tabular" name="outputFile2"/>
    <data format="pdf" name="outputFile3"/>
  </outputs>
  	
  <help> 

.. class:: infomark

**What it does**

This program generates plots and computes table matrix of maximum variances, p-values, and test orientations at multiple scales for the occurrences of a class of features in one dataset of DNA sequences using multiscale wavelet analysis technique. 

The program assumes that the user has one set of DNA sequences, S, which consists of one or more sequences of equal length. Each sequence in S is divided into the same number of multiple intervals n such that n = 2^k, where k is a positive integer and  k >= 1. Thus, n could be any value of the set {2, 4, 8, 16, 32, 64, 128, ...}. k represents the number of scales.

The program has one input file obtained as follows:

For a given set of features, say motifs, the user counts the number of occurrences of each feature in each interval of each sequence in S, and builds a tabular file representing the count results in each interval of S. This is the input file of the program. 

The program gives three output files:

- The first output file is a TABULAR format file giving the scales at which each features has a maximum variances.
- The second output file is a TABULAR format file representing the variances, p-values, and test orientation for the occurrences of features at each scale based on a random permutation test and using multiscale wavelet analysis technique.
- The third output file is a PDF file plotting the wavelet variances of each feature at each scale.

-----

.. class:: warningmark

**Note**

- If the number of features is greater than 12, the program will divide each output file into subfiles, such that each subfile represents the results of a group of 12 features except the last subfile that will represents the results of the rest. For example, if the number of features is 17, the p-values file will consists of two subfiles, the first for the features 1-12 and the second for the features 13-17. As for the PDF file, it will consists of two pages in this case.
- In order to obtain empirical p-values, a random perumtation test is implemented by the program, which results in the fact that the program gives slightly different results each time it is run on the same input file. 

-----


**Example**

Counting the occurrences of 8 features (motifs) in 16 intervals (one line per interval) of set of DNA sequences in S gives the following tabular file::

	deletionHoptspot	insertionHoptspot	dnaPolPauseFrameshift	indelHotspot	topoisomeraseCleavageSite	translinTarget		vDjRecombinationSignal		x-likeSite
		226			403			416			221		1165			832				749			1056		
		236			444			380			241		1223			746				782			1207	
		242			496			391			195		1116			643				770			1219	
		243			429			364			191		1118			694				783			1223	
		244			410			371			236		1063			692				805			1233	
		230			386			370			217		1087			657				787			1215	
		275			404			402			214		1044			697				831			1188	
		265			443			365			231		1086			694				782			1184	
		255			390			354			246		1114			642				773			1176	
		281			384			406			232		1102			719				787			1191	
		263			459			369			251		1135			643				810			1215	
		280			433			400			251		1159			701				777			1151	
		278			385			382			231		1147			697				707			1161	
		248			393			389			211		1162			723				759			1183	
		251			403			385			246		1114			752				776			1153	
		239			383			347			227		1172			759				789			1141	
  
We notice that the number of scales here is 4 because 16 = 2^4. Runnig the program on the above input file gives the following 3 output files:

The first output file::

	motifs			max_var	at scale
	deletionHoptspot		NA
	insertionHoptspot		NA
	dnaPolPauseFrameshift		NA
	indelHotspot			NA
	topoisomeraseCleavageSite	3
	translinTarget			NA
	vDjRecombinationSignal		NA
	x.likeSite			NA
	
The second output file::

	motif				1_var		1_pval		1_test		2_var		2_pval		2_test		3_var		3_pval		3_test		4_var		4_pval		4_test
	
	deletionHoptspot		0.457		0.048		L		1.18		0.334		R		1.61		0.194		R		3.41		0.055		R
	insertionHoptspot		0.556		0.109		L		1.34		0.272		R		1.59		0.223		R		2.02		0.157		R
	dnaPolPauseFrameshift		1.42		0.089		R		0.66		0.331		L		0.421		0.305		L		0.121		0.268		L
	indelHotspot			0.373		0.021		L		1.36		0.254		R		1.24		0.301		R		4.09		0.047		R
	topoisomeraseCleavageSite	0.305		0.002		L		0.936		0.489		R		3.78		0.01		R		1.25		0.272		R
	translinTarget			0.525		0.061		L		1.69		0.11		R		2.02		0.131		R		0.00891		0.069		L
	vDjRecombinationSignal		0.68		0.138		L		0.957		0.46		R		2.35		0.071		R		1.03		0.357		R
	x.likeSite			0.928		0.402		L		1.33		0.261		R		0.735		0.431		L		0.783		0.422		R

The third output file:

.. image:: ${static_path}/operation_icons/dwt_var_perClass.png

  </help>  
  
</tool>
