<tool id="MAF_To_Fasta1" name="Maf to FASTA">
    <description>Converts a MAF formated file to FASTA format</description>
    <command interpreter="python2.4">maf_to_fasta_multiple_sets.py $input1 $out_file1 $species $complete_blocks</command>
    <inputs>
        <page>
            <param format="maf" name="input1" type="data" label="MAF file"/>
        </page>
        <page>
            <param name="species" type="select" label="Species to extract" dynamic_options="get_available_species( input1.file_name )" display="checkboxes" multiple="true"/>
            <param name="complete_blocks" type="select">
              <label>Exclude blocks which have missing species</label>
              <option value="partial_allowed">No</option>
              <option value="partial_disallowed">Yes</option>
            </param>
        </page>
    </inputs>
    <outputs>
        <data format="fasta" name="out_file1" />
    </outputs>
    <tests>
      <test>
        <param name="input1" value="4.maf"/>
        <param name="species" values="canFam2,dasNov1,echTel1,hg17,loxAfr1,mm7,monDom2,oryCun1,panTro1,rheMac2,rn3"/>
        <param name="complete_blocks" value="partial_disallowed"/>
        <output name="out_file1" file="cf_maf2fasta.dat"/>
      </test>
    </tests>
    <help>

**Syntax**

This tool converts a maf formated file to FASTA format.

- **MAF format** multiple alignment format file. This format stores multiple alignments at the DNA level between entire genomes. 

  - The .maf format is line-oriented. Each multiple alignment ends with a blank line.
  - Each sequence in an alignment is on a single line.
  - Lines starting with # are considered to be comments.
  - Each multiple alignment is in a separate paragraph that begins with an "a" line and contains an "s" line for each sequence in the multiple alignment.
  - Some MAF files may contain two optional line types: 

    - An "i" line containing information about what is in the aligned species DNA before and after the immediately preceding "s" line; 
    - An "e" line containing information about the size of the gap between the alignments that span the current block.

- **FASTA format** a text-based format for representing both nucleic and protein sequences, in which base pairs or proteins are represented using a single-letter code.

  - This format contains a one line header. It starts with a " >" symbol. The first word on this line is the name of the sequence. The rest of the line is a description of the sequence.
  - The remaining lines contain the sequence itself.
  - Blank lines in a FASTA file are ignored, and so are spaces or other gap symbols (dashes, underscores, periods) in a sequence.
  - Fasta files containing multiple sequences are just the same, with one sequence listed right after another. This format is accepted for many multiple sequence alignment programs.

-----

**Example**

- MAF format::

    ##maf version=1 scoring=multiz.v7
    # multiz.v7 R=10 M=0 /cluster/bluearc/hg17/multiz.2004-07-13/danRer1/chrY.maf /cluster/bluearc/hg17/multiz.2004-07-13/panTro1mm5rn3canFam1galGal2fr1/chrY.maf -

    a score=236.0
    s hg17.chrY          3757 13 +  57701691 GATCCACTGTTCC
    s galGal2.chrUn 101379810 13 + 165033910 GCCCCGCTCACCC

    a score=418.0
    s hg17.chrY          3770 3 +  57701691 TGT
    s galGal2.chrUn 101379823 3 + 165033910 TTT
    s danRer1.chrUn 354601716 3 + 367113659 TGT

- Convert all the species of the above file to FASTA format::

    &gt;hg17.chrY(+):3757-3770|hg17_0
    GATCCACTGTTCC
    &gt;galGal2.chrUn(+):101379810-101379823|galGal2_0
    GCCCCGCTCACCC

    &gt;hg17.chrY(+):3770-3773|hg17_1
    TGT
    &gt;galGal2.chrUn(+):101379823-101379826|galGal2_1
    TTT
    &gt;danRer1.chrUn(+):354601716-354601719|danRer1_1
    TGT

    </help>
    <code file="maf_to_fasta_code.py"/>
</tool>

