<tool name="CIViC Query Report Tool" id="civic_qrt" version="0.1">
  <description>CIViC Query Report Tool reads a MAF file, calls CIViC for each line therein, and outputs a table in HTML format for easy inclusion into downstream reports</description>
  <command interpreter="python">
   civic_qrt.py
   -i "${input_file}"
   -o "${out_file}"
   -c "${host}"
   -col "${entrez_id_column}"
  </command>
  <inputs>
    <param name="input_file" type="data" format="maf" 
      label="MAF File from Oncotator" help="If empty, upload or import a MAF dataset."/>
    <param name="host" value="localhost:3000" type="text"
      label="Host to query from" size="80" 
      help="Query from the CIViC server"/>
    <param name="entrez_id_column" value="1" type="text"
     label="Entrez ID column number in MAF file. Default:1" size="10"
     help="Entrez ID column number in MAF file. Default:1"/>
  </inputs>
  <outputs>
    <data format="html" name="out_file" label="CIViC Summary with links to webpage."/>
  </outputs>
  <tests>
    <test>
    </test>
  </tests>
  
  <help>

.. class:: infomark


**PURPOSE**

CIViC Query Report Tool is a simple command line tool that reads a MAF file, calls CIViC for each line therein. It outputs a table in HTML format for easy inclusion into downstream reports

CIViCReader requires Python 2.*. To check your python version, run: python -V

**INPUTS, OUTPUTS AND PARAMETERS**

$ python civic_reader.py -h

usage: civic_reader [-h] [-i INPUT_FILE] [-o OUTPUT_FILE] [-c HOST] [-col ENTREZ_ID_COLUMN]

      -h, --help            show this help message and exit
      -i INPUT_FILE, --input_file INPUT_FILE
                            input file (assumed to be tab separated MAF format); defaults to stdin
      -o OUTPUT_FILE, --output_file OUTPUT_FILE
                            output file; defaults to stdout
      -c HOST, --host HOST  url of reference civic host; Default:civic.genome.wustl.edu
      --col ENTREZ_ID_COLUMN, --entrez_id_column ENTREZ_ID_COLUMN
                            column in the input file that contains the entrez id; Default(0 based): 1

**PROCESS**

On entry CIViCReader reads all variants from CIViC for a particular gene, using entrez_id as the gene identifier.

If there is no data returned from CIViC, CIViCReader displays gene not found in civic and moves on.

If there is data returned from CIViC, CIViCReader searches the CIViC EvidenceItems returned and matches on {Chromosome}:{Start_position}-{End_position} ({Reference_Allele}->{Tumor_Seq_Allele1})

If there is a match CIViCReader displays [civic variant] with a link to the specific variant in CIViC
Otherwise CIViCReader displays [civic gene] with a link to the gene in CIViC

**CIViC**

For further details about CIViC, please go to: https://civic.genome.wustl.edu

  </help>
</tool>












